Finding Aid for American Council on Alcohol Problems Records 1883-2015
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Reports and Minutes
  Material for 1931 includes information concerning: the legality of constitutional conventions; A.S.L.A. constitutional arguments against resubmission of the 18th Amendment; prohibition legislation facts compiled by the A.S.L.A.; a history of prohibition legislation prior to the 18th Amendment; the legality of fermented fruit juices and cider; the Havell Bill for prohibition in the District of Columbia (a copy of the bill is included); and other reports of the Legal and Legislative Office.
  Reports and Minutes for 1932 contain information concerning: state laws dealing with 2.75% beer; A.S.L.A. policy when neither major political party supported prohibition; the 1932 A.S.L.A. convention; the repeal movement and state constitutional conventions; state decisions on initiative and referendum; beer as an intoxicating beverage; the status of state prohibition legislation in case the 18th Amendment was repealed; incorporation of the Nebraska Anti-Saloon League; and the "Resist Repeal" convention, December 9-12, 1932 in Washington, D.C.
  Reports and Minutes for 1933 deal primarily with legal aspects of state constitutional conventions and the repeal movement, including an outline of the argument against repeal; a statement on methods of electing dry delegates to state conventions; information about state liquor laws and constitutional conventions; and copies of Congressional repeal bills. There are also reports on the most effective state enforcement laws, including the Arizona Control Act and the Colorado Beer Act, and the 1933 report of the A.S.L.A. Legal and Legislative Office.
  - Undated 1912-1932, 23 folders (Box 2)
  - 1933-1949, 25 folders (Box 3)
  - 1950-1968, 6 folders (Box 4)
- Lincoln-Lee Legion
  (organization established to encourage individuals to take pledge against alcohol consumption)
  - 1933-1941, 8 folders (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks and published materials
  Scrapbooks and published materials include a 1927 scrapbook containing obituaries of Wayne B. Wheeler and statements by national leaders concerning Wheeler's career, written shortly after his death. There are also contains copies of the A.S.L.A. publication, Prohibition Enforcement Bulletin, 1922-1923.
  - Scrapbook concerning the Anti-Saloon League annual convention 1938 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook concerning the death of Wayne B. Wheeler (Box 4)
  - Prohibition Enforcement Bulletin, 1922-1923 (Box 4)
- Regional Activities
  Regional Activities concern the activities of state A.S.L.A. organizations in Virginia, Oklahoma and the District of Columbia. Papers, 1916-1927, concerning A.S.L. activities in Oklahoma include: copies of Oklahoma prohibition laws; a syllabus of an Oklahoma Supreme Court case concerning transportation of liquor; a copy of Oklahoma Senate Bill No. 61, relating to government regulation of liquor sales; two issues of The American Issue: Oklahoma Edition, April, 1913 and April, 1916; copies of several state bills concerning prohibition restrictions and enforcement; a speech by U.S. Senator Robert L. Owen concerning the Sedition Bill; a letter from the Federal Prohibition Director of Oklahoma urging greater publicity for prohibition laws by government officers and civic organizations; and an application for a writ of habeas corpus from a man convicted of prohibition violations.
  Papers, 1917-1921, concerning A.S.L. activities in Virginia include: a copy of the Virginia Prohibition Act, approved March 10, 1916; an A.S.L. statement on the liquor trade, which provides a good synopsis of A.S.L. ideology; a statement (1919) of Virginia's Commissioner of Prohibition on the decline of crime since the state adopted prohibition; the Commissioner's first annual report; editorials on the lack of prohibition enforcement in the state; copies of and articles about state prohibition regulations; a report stating that one county lost more tax money from liquor's creation of criminals than it gained from license fees; a copy of Virginia's Layman Prohibition Law (amended 1928); and a report on proposed amendments to the Virginia Constitution. Next is a folder of correspondence, 1907-1915, of the District of Columbia Anti-Saloon League. This consists primarily of copies of outgoing letters from A. E. Shoemaker, Attorney for the A.S.L., dealing with efforts to block liquor license applications, questions concerning license fees, and other daily activities.
  - Oklahoma 1916-1927 (Box 4)
  - Virginia 1917-1930, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - District of Columbia
    - 1907-1915 (Box 4)
    - 1964 (Box 4)
- Speeches
  Speeches are mostly those of Congressmen on bills affecting prohibition. The Speeches contains printed speeches primarily by members of Congress, many of them published in the Congressional Record, and Congressional Committee reports concerning prohibition issues. Speeches, 1911-1919, are by Richmond P. Hobson, William S. Kenyon, Woodrow Wilson, and Richard Yates; and Congressional Committee reports on prohibition bills and hearings. Speeches, 1920-1922, are on prohibition and law enforcement, by A. J. Volstead, Morris Sheppard, William D. Upshaw, Harry M. Daugherty, Thomas L. Blanton, Knute Nelson, Guy D. Goff, A. P. Nelson, Louis C. Cramton, Roy A. Haynes, Thomas Sterling, and others; and an "Explanatory Statement" dealing with the Supplemental Prohibition Enforcement Bill.
  Speeches, 1923-1925, are by Louis C. Cramton, Walter F. Lineberger, Israel M. Foster, L. J. Dickinson, John G. Cooper, Thomas Sterling, William D. Upshaw, Richard Yates, John W. Summers, Alben W. Barkley, and others; and reports on the Supplemental Prohibition Act, "Enforcement of the Eighteenth Amendment," a Congressional hearing "To Establish an Independent Prohibition Bureau," and hearings on extension of civil service regulations to prohibition agents.
  Speeches dated 1926-1927 consist of addresses concerning prohibition by Clyde Kelly, Wesley L. Jones, John N. Tillman, John W. Summers, John G. Cooper, Grant M. Hudson, Edward E. Browne, Lamar Jeffers, B. G. Lowrey, W. T. Fitzgerald, Louis C. Cramton, William E. Borah, William G. McAdoo, and Miles C. Allgood. Speeches, 1928-1929, are by William G. McAdoo, James Cannon, Jr., J. Thomas Heflin, Grant M. Hudson, Morris Sheppard, Hugo L. Black, Wesley L. Jones, Lawrence D. Tyson, William E. Borah, Arthur Capper, Ernest H. Cherrington and others. Speeches for 1930-1933 include prohibition-related addresses by Morris Sheppard, Wesley L. Jones, James Cannon, Jr., Franklin W. Fort, Arthur Capper, James M. Beck, F. Scott McBride, Carroll L. Beedy, Leonidas C. Dyer, Smith W. Brookhart, Maurice H. Thatcher, Clarence F. Lea, and other Congressmen. Also included is the report of hearings on the "Border Patrol" by the Senate Committee on Commerce.
  - 1911-1942, 7 folders (Box 4)
- Congressional bills relating to prohibition
  Congressional bills are those bills which the Legal and Legislative Office considered important and lobbied to pass or defeat. Congressional Bills concerning prohibition, 1912-1919 include copies of bills to regulate liquor traffic in the District of Columbia; resolutions proposing a national prohibition amendment; bills to repeal the National German-American Alliance; resolutions concerning war-time prohibition and liquor issues; Volstead's bill "To prohibit intoxicating beverages and to regulate the production and use of other alcoholic liquors"; Senate Judiciary subcommittee hearings on "Prohibiting Intoxicating Beverages" (345 pp.); reports on prohibition; and the National Prohibition Act (H.R.6810).
  Congressional Bills concerning prohibition, 1920-1922 includes hearings on "Safeguarding of Liquor in Bonded Warehouses"; bills supplemental to the National Prohibition Act; bills concerning various aspects of prohibition; and typed lists of Congressional bills and resolutions related to prohibition.
  Congressional Bills for 1923 includes bills and joint resolutions concerning: veterans' benefits; amendments to the National Prohibition Act; deportation of aliens who violate the National Prohibition Act; exclusion of Asiatic laborers from immigration to the United States; prohibition enforcement and regulation; and Constitutional amendment procedures.
  Bills and resolutions for 1924 includes proposals concerning: purchase of liquor from a "bootlegger" as grounds for impeachment of any government employee; prohibition of foreign diplomats from transporting or dispensing liquor in the United States; revisions of the National Prohibition Act; prohibition enforcement and regulation; deportation of "certain undesirable aliens"; establishment of a Bureau of Prohibition in the Treasury Department; appropriations for various departments of government; a Constitutional amendment to regulate child labor; United States participation in international conferences for control of the narcotic drug traffic; limitation of the immigration of aliens; repeal of the 18th Amendment (H.J. Res. 273, May 29, 1924); and other government activities. The folder for March-April, 1924 contains approximately 60 different bills "To amend the National Prohibition Act."
  Congressional Bills, 1925-1930, concern: deportation of aliens; salaries of Postal Service employees; amendments to the National Prohibition Act; prohibition enforcement; proposed changes in procedures of Federal courts; and applications by state legislatures for calling a national constitutional convention.
  - 1912-1930, 7 folders (Box 5)
- Financial Materials
  Financial Materials for 1928 consist of the A.S.L.A. Budget Report, January 1 - June 30, 1928, containing departmental budgetary accounts, budgetary apportionments by states, and fund collections and expenses by states, for the A.S.L.A. and the World League Against Alcoholism. Financial Papers for 1930 consist of a Budget Report and a Report of Audit. The Budget Report includes budgetary statements for the A.S.L.A. and general financial statements for the A.S.L.A., the American Issue Publishing Company, the World League Against Alcoholism and the A.S.L.A. Educational Foundation. The Report of Audit for the A.S.L.A. contains an analysis of departmental expense accounts, a statement of funds, a detailed analysis of expenses, and other financial records.
  Financial Papers for 1931 consists of the Report of Audit, June 30, 1931, for the World League Against Alcoholism; the Report of Audit for the A.S.L.A.; and an estimate of cash payments due during November, 1931 for these two organizations. Financial Papers for 1932 consists of A.S.L.A. "New Subscription Reports" from the Anti-Saloon League Field Day, January 17, 1932; an estimate of cash payments due during March, 1932; and a few miscellaneous lists of speakers and subscription amounts.
  - 1928-1951, 22 folders (Box 5)
- National Temperance and Prohibition Council
  - 1934-1956, 3 folders (Box 5)
- Legal Files
  Legal Files contain a number of briefs of Federal and state cases which either directly involved the A.S.L.A. or demanded close attention due to their relation to prohibition laws. Undated Legal Files include: a lengthy "Memorandum Concerning Indictments Against the United States Brewers' Association, and Various Brewing Corporations in the State of Pennsylvania"; the printed brief of defendants in an Ohio Supreme Court case dealing with illegal sale of liquor; statements concerning forfeiture statutes in several states; printed briefs for court cases involving illegal liquor sales in West Virginia and a Pennsylvania Congressional election contested by the Prohibition Party candidate; a libel suit against Wayne B. Wheeler and others; a suit against Louis C. Cramton; a brief for an Ohio prohibition case; and a list of "Cases Holding Contrary View and Grounds of Distinction Upon Which They Rest."
  Legal Files for 1919 include briefs and other information concerning: Joseph E. Everard v. James Everard's Breweries, et al., which related to the effects of war-time prohibition; Hoffman Brewing Company v. Eisner, et al., which disputed the war prohibition regulations; copy of a letter from Attorney General A. Mitchell Palmer to Secretary of State Robert Lansing, May 8, 1919, discussing legal aspects of the Reed Amendment concerning interstate transportation of liquor; copy of a letter from Palmer to Lansing, December 5, 1919, concerning effects of the Prohibition Amendment; the Supreme Court opinion in Ruppert v. Caffey, concerning the Volstead Act; and information concerning other cases related to prohibition and liquor questions. Also included is a brief for Everard's Breweries v. Ralph A. Day, et al., which claimed that the Supplemental Prohibition Act of November 23, 1921 was unconstitutional.
  Legal Files for 1921 contains: a brief in behalf of Hiram Walker and Sons of Canada, concerning shipment of liquors through the United States to another foreign country; Supreme Court briefs concerning whether liquor stored in a Government bonded warehouse can be removed by the warehouse owner for consumption as a beverage; briefs in the case of Lipke v. Lederer, concerning collection of taxes for liquor under the National Prohibition Act; legal papers concerning several cases dealing with the liquor operations tax; and other prohibition-related cases.
  Legal Files for 1922 contains: summaries of legal decisions and precedents related to prohibition; a brief for Piel Brothers v. Ralph A. Day, et al., dealing with enforcement of the National Prohibition Law; the Supreme Court decision in Lipke v. Lederer and a statement discussing the case's implications; a list of state regulations dealing with "Taxation as a means to discourage the prohibited traffic"; and briefs and other legal papers concerning various prohibition cases.
  Legal Files for 1923 contains briefs and other legal papers concerning various cases related to prohibition, including: Piel Brothers v. Day; Everard v. Day; Lambert v. Yellowley; Cunard Steamship Company v. Mellon; and Carroll v. United States. These files also contain a copy of a letter from Charles E. Hughes to A. J. Volstead discussing the Cramton Bill regarding liquor in foreign embassies; a synopsis of search and seizure laws relating to intoxicating liquors; a Supreme Court brief for respondents in a suit to require the New York A.S.L. to report its finances connected with the 1922 election campaign; a "Synopsis of record in cases attacking validity of anti-beer bill"; a statement concerning unlawful movement of intoxicating liquors; and a memorandum for Prohibition Commissioner Haynes concerning Rep. John P. Hill of Maryland, who was accused of producing fermented grape juice in his home.
  Cases dealing directly with prohibition are less numerous in the Legal Files for 1924 than cases dealing with indirectly related issues such as civil rights, judicial power of the Supreme Court, applications for writs of habeas corpus, power of the President to pardon contempt violations of the Volstead Act, and contempt of court rulings. There is also information concerning the Volstead Act's constitutionality; unlawful transportation of liquor; United States v. John P. Hill; Hixson v. Oakes; Brambini v. U.S.; and R. O. Johnson, et al. v. U.S.
  Legal Files for 1925 contains information about: due process of law; U.S. v. Hill; Lambert v. Yellowley; Druggan v. Anderson; and briefs for several other prohibition-related cases. A memorandum from the Federal Prohibition Commissioner's office to Wayne B. Wheeler, offering advice on handling two prohibition cases, suggests a spirit of cooperation between the government and the A.S.L.A.
  Legal Files for 1926 contains manuscript material related to three prohibition cases: Tumey v. State of Ohio; the Jack Daniel conspiracy case; and Lambert v. Yellowley. There are also several printed briefs for Tumey v. State of Ohio, as well as printed briefs for Dodge v. United States and for an application for a writ of habeas corpus.
  Legal Files, 1927-1930, contains: information about the income tax on illegal liquor traffic; a brief for Kirchner v. Walter, concerning whether the Ohio liquor tax was constitutional; a letter from Assistant Attorney General Mable W. Willebrandt, discussing forfeitures under the National Prohibition Act; an address on forfeiture by Vincent Simonton, Assistant Counsel of the Bureau of Prohibition; a copy of the charge to the jury in the Virginia Dare Vineyards case; and material concerning other prohibition cases.
  Legal Files for 1933 contains papers related to legal efforts to block state ratification conventions in Arizona, California, Pennsylvania, Michigan, Ohio, Missouri and Vermont. These briefs, petitions, abstracts and opinions reveal several arguments and tactics adopted by opponents of prohibition repeal.
  - Undated 1919-1959, 24 folders (Box 6)
    (scattered dates)
- Pamphlets
  Pamphlets cover a wide range of topics from the harmful effects of liquor to how the Federal government should provide better control over the illegal liquor traffic.
  Undated Pamphlets include many pamphlets and leaflets describing the background, principles and operations of the Anti-Saloon League and various aspects of temperance and prohibition. They include "To Drink or Not to Drink," "Wet Slanders of Abraham Lincoln Refuted," "Catholics and Prohibition," "The Battle for National Prohibition," and other articles by Edward B. Dunford, Wayne B. Wheeler, William E. Johnson, Ernest H. Cherrington, Cora Frances Stoddard, Evangeline Booth, and other prohibition supporters.
  Pamphlets, 1883-1918, contain: addresses and sermons concerning the harmful medical effects of alcohol, the cost of alcoholic beverages to consumers, and religious arguments against liquor license laws; the A.S.L. "Blue Book," entitled "The Church in Action Against the Saloon"; "The Birth of the Anti-Saloon League"; and pamphlets concerning prohibition laws and the effects of liquor. Pamphlets for 1919 consist of "The Eighteenth Amendment," by Wayne B. Wheeler; the report of Congressional hearings on enforcement of prohibition; and a Congressional report by A. J. Volstead on "Prohibiting Intoxicating Beverages."
  Pamphlets, 1920-1922, consist of printed materials concerning prohibition and prohibition organizations, including: the annual report of the New Zealand Alliance for the Abolition of the Liquor Traffic; copies of United States prohibition laws; the annual report of the Virginia Commissioner of Prohibition; "The Prohibition Question, Viewed from the Economic and Moral Standpoint"; the program for the International Convention of the World League Against Alcoholism; and several leaflets regarding prohibition.
  Pamphlets for 1923 include: "Beer: Is it Intoxicating Liquor?"; "Laws Relating to National Prohibition Enforcement," published by the Internal Revenue Service; President Harding's address on law enforcement; extracts from Congressional hearings on establishment of an independent prohibition bureau; and other materials concerning prohibition enforcement, search and seizure regulations, and the effects of making liquor easily available.
  Pamphlets dated 1924 include: Ernest H. Cherrington's "Report on Behalf of the American Committee on International Relations"; "Regulations Relative to Intoxicating Liquor," published by the Prohibition Unit of the Bureau of Internal Revenue; the report and addresses of the Woman's National Convention for Law Enforcement; extracts from Congressional hearings on manufacture and sale of 2.75% beverages; and other pamphlets concerning prohibition.
  Pamphlets for 1925 include: information concerning the International Reform Federation; "Is Prohibition a Success After Five Years?," by Wayne B. Wheeler; the annual report of the Legal and Legislative Department of the A.S.L.A., by Wheeler and Edward B. Dunford; articles from The Ohio Law Bulletin and Reporter concerning prohibition cases; and other materials.
  Pamphlets for 1926 include: "The League's Policy in the Smith-Brennan Campaign" in Illinois; articles citing the economic benefits of prohibition; "Proposed Amendments to the Constitution" (1889-1926); an address by Howard Hyde Russell; and other materials concerning various A.S.L.A. interests.
  Pamphlets dated 1927 include: a biographical sketch of Herbert C. Hoover; "The 18th Amendment," by Edward B. Dunford; a Senate report on "Denaturization of Industrial Alcohol"; a Bureau of Prohibition report on permits for manufacture of and traffic in intoxicating liquors; the report of the A.S.L.A. Legal and Legislative Department, by Dunford; and other printed materials.
  Pamphlets for 1928 contain: materials concerning state and national elections; "Alcoholism Mortality as a Problem of Health Officials," by Cora Frances Stoddard; "Education Against Alcoholism," by Ernest H. Cherrington; articles about Herbert Hoover; "Kernel Corn of Kentucky," a novelette exposing the methods employed in trying to head off prohibition in the South; "Some Factors Influencing the Toxic Effect of Alcohol"; addresses to the legislature by Governors Alfred Smith of New York and Harry F. Byrd of Virginia; a copy of Virginia's Layman Prohibition Law; and other printed materials concerning prohibition.
  Pamphlets dated 1929 include: "They Almost Had Me Fooled," which refutes criticisms and misrepresentations regarding prohibition; "Proposed Amendments to the Constitution," a compilation of facts published by Congress; an address on making the 18th Amendment effective, by Senator Wesley L. Jones; "Education: The Only Permanent Solution of the Alcohol Problem," by Ernest H. Cherrington; "The Problem and Policy of Prohibition," by Commissioner of Prohibition James M. Doran; proposed revisions of the National Prohibition Act; and other materials concerning prohibition.
  Pamphlets for 1930-1931 include: a report of the work of the American Issue Publishing Company, 1910-1930, by Ernest H. Cherrington; the report of the Legal, Legislative and Executive Departments of the A.S.L.A., by Francis Scott McBride and Edward B. Dunford; "After Ten Years," an address by James J. Britt, Chief Counsel of the Bureau of Prohibition, before the A.S.L.A. national meeting in Detroit; "Educating the Masses and the Classes Against Alcoholism," by Cherrington; "The Cigarette as a Physician Sees It"; a report on prohibition enforcement, by the National Commission on Law Observance and Enforcement, and other prohibition materials.
  Pamphlets dated 1932 include: a compilation of Virginia "Prohibition Law Amendments"; "Hoover's Betrayal of National Prohibition"; "Constitutional Aspects of National Prohibition," discussing its antecedents, objections to repeal and advisability of modification; the report of the Legal and Legislative Departments, by E.B. Dunford and F. S. McBride; the annual report of the Women's National Committee for Law Enforcement; "Proceedings of the Board of Directors" of the A.S.L.A. at the Washington conference (December 9-13, 1932); Senate committee hearings on amending the National Prohibition Act; and other printed materials concerning prohibition. Pamphlets for 1933 consist of three items: Senate Committee hearings on modification of the Volstead Act; House committee hearings on taxation of "nonintoxicating liquor"; and "Education Against Alcoholism," E. H. Cherrington's report and preview of educational efforts of the World League Against Alcoholism and the A.S.L.A. Department of Education.
  - Undated 1883-1959, 24 folders (Box 7)
- Photographs
  - Portraits, photographs of meetings, etc. circa 1910s-1930s, 5 folders (Box 8)
    (also 1 oversize folder, UBJl)
  - 4th Annual Southern Prohibition Convention undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Anti-Saloon League Convention, St. Petersburg, FL undated (Box 9, Folder 1)